All right, we start.
You can read a lot of papers and people are still working on this.
People, you will find people are still improving, improve, or based on this transformer.
this picture you will see something like this.
didn't get well. Okay, we review our, today we introduced transformer. So transformer is a
In one way, you write the mean into the matrix multiplication format.
The encoder is here already, right?
If you have opportunity, thank you for coming.
So maybe you have patch normalization,
So the formula is hidden state not only affected by the input and the previous hidden state, but also the context vector we call it C.
Okay, actually, water queries, water key values.
So each row is actually the vector position there.
You are finished, processed all the input.
Normalization, I think, okay.
You tell your friends, okay?
layer normalization, instance normalization,
So from the decoder, you can see all the tokens from encoder, right?
Not the year two, you are familiar with the environment.
Okay, let's start.
So we go through this one by one.
model architecture, how input, how output, input is the whole sequence. Okay, in code calculate
And then, okay, here you don't need to understand.
So, OK, q1, q2, q3.
groups normalization, a lot.
That does not mean you can stop learning.
This is the vector position Y.
We talk about self-attention.
So attention is all you need.
Okay, we start from attention.
Time is this matrix.
Until now you don't need to understand.
I can stop going to classroom.
That's true.
Okay, the encoder contents, self attention layers.
If you extend the dimension to 128,
I hope you are familiar with matrix multiplication times this.
What is self-attention?
You already know, the input is a lot of vectors, but there is something called a query.
Transformers network architecture,
You still need to learn a lot of things.
We still need to review this iron-based encoder and decoder.
You can see all the positions of the output of the encoder.
So what is this C? Okay, where is someone? We for each hidden state.
All of the keys, values, queries,
OK, q1, times q1, y.
so clear.
So you tell people who are not here.
all the information of the input sequence. So the input are mapped to query, key and value,
like CNN, convolution on your networks.
One thing you need to understand is for each position is a vector,
What is the query?
comes from the same place.
But your general, only generate the output sequence one by one.
And the output is a vector also.
q2, times q1, q3, times q1, and sum them together.
And a long time ago, I said, okay,
The query is hidden state from the decoder.
Okay, plus this hidden state as there. Okay.
Come from the same place, means the input times different with matrix.
But Transformers has no recurrence,
The output is computed as a weighted sum.
we are simple and with some numbers to show what is different between a fee forward neural network and the RNN.
This thing query the output of the encoder.
So here comes problem.
not a single number.
no conclusions, okay.
You will get alpha 0 0.
That means, okay, for when you when you predict every French what? Okay, review the whole English sentence again.
And the weight is the compatibility function of the query with the corresponding key.
So they can be added to the token embedding.
Pure attention.
You cannot see the future tokens, right?
In this case, the output of the previous layer in the encoder,
The Transformers don't have this arrow.
OK, also what is this dot product?
by multiply different matrix. That's why we call it self attention, because there's no other
Okay, so key and value, hidden states of the encoder.
if you input, of course, in the middle layer,
Then this complex formulas are just used to calculate the values of different dimension.
That you haven't predicted yet.
Go back.
Dot product between q1 and q1.
You may see this picture a lot of times.
Of course, during training, you know I know all the output ground tools already.
My imagination is that you have some equipment, you know, a handwriting.
But here, called self-attention.
output of the previous layer.
Now we go back.
Okay.
Here also your question, okay, where does this query key value come from?
information source. All these query, key, value come from the input. In the middle layer,
Today the mantascus, we read this picture
So each position in the encoder can attend to all positions.
Okay, attention means there is a query.
You will get the first number, the first score.
But now, finally, I didn't make it.
Okay, easy to understand.
But in the inference stage, you only generate it by one, by two.
So let's basically the structure of the I am based in code anti-coder for a motion translation.
Of course, there are some reasonably designed ways.
Oh, see, here the query is hidden state.
So, similarly, you get the second, the fourth,
So I have to change to this traditional slice format.
Self-attention means come from self.
So what does this mean?
one box by one box.
Actually, this is a research direction.
That means, let me find something.
And the key and value are all hidden states.
the input is the output of the previous layer. Attention means, okay, you have a set of values,
So the input sequence,
You don't know Y3, Y4, right?
Every after today's lecture,
In the encoder, there's no recurrent,
and you write into the format of matrix multiplication.
So why do we...
Okay, until now, any questions. Yeah, this also review. Okay, now in code processes and encodes the information from all input elements.
Sorry.
And the output is a weighted sum.
I hope you can understand every single box
How do you calculate the attention?
X is linearly transformed to produce the query key and value.
One, I don't ask you, one important thing about position is,
so the whole sequence is input in one time.
But, okay, I still can explain the problem.
Okay, output weighted sum of hidden states.
of this picture.
OK, and after you, these are just the numbers.
How do you do almost all the calculations?
Okay.
Okay, every position can see all the inputs.
We also start from a task, okay.
you want to, attend, right, you want to notice only important things. So the output is the
So here is a fee forward neural network, familiar with.
actually, the length of the sequence.
How do you calculate the weight?
Start from a task like a,
And in all the modern calculations, all matrix, right?
Sometimes these numbers are really high.
Okay, that means, okay, all the input sequence will here.
When you are training, you have a dataset.
Okay, the weight is assigned to each value is computed by a compatibility function of the query with the corresponding key.
The input is vector.
imagine a translation task, okay.
Okay, every position can see all the inputs.
Okay, we input an English sentence. Okay, we believe all the meaning of this English sentence start in this state.
This is 100.
This vector has three dimensions.
We don't do one by one, we calculate matrix.
Okay, suppose the longest sequence in this training set is just 100 words.
This is negative 2 minus 2.
It is, we call it a sequence to sequence problem.
And multiply by matrix, three different matrix, the form query key and value.
Let's say, okay, so this sequence,
So how do we prevent leftover information flowing in the decoder?
weighted sum of these values. Okay, how to get the weightage of each value. There are some keys,
So, we go to a soft matrix.
This w is the parameter.
The input is a sequence of words,
each position in encoder can attend to all positions.
The parameter we are going to learn, also called weight, weight matrix.
But in the real one, in the inference state,
As a soft matrix, remember the soft matrix.
as an English word.
A compatibility function is, okay, as times sum matrix parameter plus, okay, plus this one.
Okay, and the decoder generate target output and utilize this information. Okay, this information is the most important and alley information source of decoder.
So we mask out, there is something called mask, mask.
The output is a sequence of French words.
you may meet a sequence with one soldier.
Until now, it looks normal, guys,
Soft matrix comes with values to 0 between 0 and y
And after the first layer, you will get this.
So basically they come from same thing, come from self.
And how do we do it?
for the, it's prepared for the decoder part,
You set the value, out of the value in the matrix to very large negative numbers.
Okay. How do we do it?
you need to calculate the relevance between query and different keys. After you calculate the
Most of the time, the model will perform very bad.
So we analyze this task first.
later, you'll see.
This one key, okay, the weight is here, activity, after the time activity, activation function.
We call it hidden state.
Because they times different parameters, so they form different values,
to the probability distribution.
So we can see the input, the input sentence.
Okay, residual connections,
H equals to w times x.
Because the model never see such a long sequence.
this here, these two lines,
OK, then this one is 100.
and this add, okay, two lines, add, residual connections.
Okay, let's say, that way you calculate, no matter what you calculate,
That means the input x is mapped into the hidden state, hidden representation.
We know all of the input sentence,
So how does the decoding process begin? If I give a special token began our sequence.
Very large number becomes 0.9.
they become query key and value.
So the position is one of the...
relevant score like dot product, you need to apply soft max, map it to probability distribution.
That's one, h2, okay, plus this is a key to query.
but we don't know the output sentence.
So what's the motivation of residual?
That's why they call self-attention.
Very small number becomes 0.0, 0.1, a soft matrix.
the weight is zero, no matter what you calculate, no matter what you calculate.
So some model, okay.
One of the easy ones, you need to concentrate.
What is, what is the residual?
It has four dimensions.
For the first layer, it's input for the middle layer and output previously.
Here's a very simple sum point.
Okay, what if I see a sequence much longer in the training dataset?
Some model, I think most of the model
The deep models may forget previous learning information,
So how does the decoding process stop? People give us special token and now sequence. Okay, one decoder predict.
And the value is this.
It's a very, very large negative value.
Okay, clear.
choose we predict the output tokens one by one.
What is a query?
Don't forget the values.
We are using another weight matrix to map to output.
That's easier to calculate, then you get the weight, you get the values, you get the attention.
but you will find a lot of description like this.
So, imagine now I'm teaching you some problem like a transformer, right?
Okay, clear.
And you go to a softer mask.
Now you get the weight between different queries and different keys.
How do we handle this?
When the sequence becomes very long,
So just take note, they times different matrix, so they are different values.
Okay.
The start concentrate many, many different aspects.
Okay, in the neural network, we don't want the values becomes too large or too small,
the model may forget the previous information.
Okay, similar to other tokens. I also for each step have a probability. I have a probability.
We do not have much good message to predict the whole sentence.
The no way that becomes zero point, zero, the whole lot of zero, right?
But here we only focus on this input and hidden state.
You need to find some knowledge from your mind, from your own knowledge database.
For example, relative position.
So when the model becomes very deep,
The output is the weighted sum of different values.
No problem, right?
And dot product attention, we said, okay, we use dot product to calculate the relationship
Not only the one sentence, this one sentence is 100 words.
they may forget previous learning information.
We predict the whole sentence once,
One.
So basically you ignore the vector, you cannot see.
This is a fee forward neural network.
So when the decoder predict, okay, we have a zero point nine probability. We we next the token is EOS and now sequence.
Actually, you learn a lot of things, right?
you want time, you want step.
And, yeah, the use for signals becomes,
OK, weighted sum of different values.
And here is the second input.
Other values, and you can like summarize or abstract them into some concepts, okay?
because we need the graded, but for some activation function like sigmoid, if the value is too large
So this is mask.
But they have two words of same relative distance.
So we predict first, first, okay.
There are also three dimensions.
Then you have this weight.
or the relevance between query and keys.
If we have time later, we can see in the code.
forget, okay, what do we do?
You have all the values, you multiply, and sum them together.
But the values are different.
And according to the input and the tokens,
Okay, same relative distance.
Very straightforward, very straightforward.
Three, zero point three.
If you read the paper, okay, okay, your fan is too picturesque.
So this is the mask, multi-head attention, okay?
Okay, then the procedure stop and when the sequence is too long, the neural network may forget the English sentence.
So this kind of formula, capture, capture, information, okay, relative, relative.
Same, same with matrix.
We, we input, okay, we copied the previous information again, okay?
I say you already learned neural network.
or too small, the graded becomes narrow. When the graded becomes narrow, your neural network did not
You get the final output.
Query and key dot product, because they are matrix, many queries, many keys.
we already predict, we predict next token one by one.
Actually, neural network is a concept.
After your times, you get this hidden representation or hidden state.
And neural network have a lot of things.
Some more, you have the weight 0.9.
Because you cannot see the future, you only see the tokens,
And there's one good thing is this single soil encoding is pretty fun.
So, this neural network is one of the key.
You times the value, you get out of y.
So question comes immediately, okay.
So we input to the hidden state for every step every step. Okay, so any problems, right, any problems.
There is different values.
They use a variable for what, okay?
update anymore. So the learning procedure is stopped. So to prevent this, we use normalization
The values of the neural network, okay, I'll explain, input, output, and weightage, the activation function, the loss, etc.
you already predicted.
So it's a mathematic multiplication.
0.0, 0.1, you times the value, you get the output,
One does this, what is the first token?
Clear.
A lot of information to flow directly across layers.
But now we add, we call it add some recurrent item here.
Okay, let's go to next.
I don't need training.
How do we select the first token?
This is called encoder decoder attention.
What skill?
So it's computational efficient.
you sum them together.
So people are smart.
Okay?
Sometimes they give the first token a special token,
That means you're simply,
Then you get the output.
We are using r and n.
Skill, I mean, divided by square root or decay.
And of course, no matter how long it is, you can have a value.
Actually, you'll see this before, right?
before it is Y equals to FX,
Okay, so what attention does?
to normalize values into the ranges under control. Okay, but if you have a batch data, if you have a
OK, I think a little bit difficult, but OK, how do we write down into the formula?
RN encoder, decoder, it is encoder decoder attention.
Okay.
Very clear, right, can this context to work to contain all the information.
And we, as we said, hidden state, H2, this one is not only primary.
that is built for formula,
called Begin of Sequence.
If you talk about it later, skill, divided by the square root of decay,
In fact, calculation, you can have a value.
Okay, query is, okay, I'm going to learn transformer, you start thinking, okay, what do I know?
atomic deep neural network,
Later we show this, okay.
That means the query comes from the decoder.
So people still do research on this.
but they find that, okay, I add a deep model
OK, remember you get the alpha after you calculate this score.
And second question, okay.
forget previous information.
When do we stop?
Sorry, this way, can this as their content all the information.
The RIG, evaluation, transformer, R&N, something, okay?
the dimension of key, softmax, it becomes the weightage, becomes 0.9, 0.01,
We predict next token, predict the next token.
What do we do?
Aspects, they are aimed to improve in conclude.
batch of sequence data, you need to present some technology, batch normalization, layer normalization,
H2, sorry.
Okay, we plus X again.
But the key and the values comes from the encoder.
You get alpha 0, alpha 0, y alpha 0, 2.
H2 is not only affected by the input, but also affected by the hidden state, the previous hidden state.
Under this.
Generalization to longer sequences, relative positions, and stability, of course, efficiency.
You plus the input.
So people add under of sequence token.
I cannot see a parent in a card not a red, but a large chance cannot write this H3 kind of content all the information.
Okay, you'll find some similar or related concepts, these are keys.
Okay, you forget it, right?
Okay, this is easy to understand.
After you go through the soft matrix, we still call them.
Okay, I copied it to you.
So every step we predict, okay.
times value, output.
You have some input, you have an input, an English sentence.
What do we do?
Is this the end of sequence?
So what's the result?
Okay, you'll give each key some weight.
etc., etc. But the key idea is keep the value in the range that we can control it.
Okay, that's basically all for today.
The result is actually FX becomes Y minus X.
Yeah, alpha 0, alpha 0, y.
Okay, remember the previous hidden state is, uh, the report to the report to the report six.
It is an stop.
And then you follow multi-hydrate attention, you'll hear that.
You must have some method to send this information to the decoder.
Why don't we see all the hidden states? Why don't we use all the hidden states? Okay, of course we can. We use all the hidden states.
Let's say, okay, I want to recall a few forward neural network and R&N.
So today is a little bit difficult, but I think important.
So if you see this two special sign,
And then for each score, you times the value.
We save this value somewhere, somewhere.
Attention, attention, attention.
This is a method that query comes from the decoder.
Okay, when the model is too deep, the model may forget previous information. So people input,
you should be familiar, you should know them.
Y minus X means FX only learn a small refinement.
What is multi-hydrate attention?
You times the value, 1, 1 becomes this, and then report, y 0, y.
You have three vectors.
And then we, as you know, we calculate this H2 first.
So people find it is beneficial to linearly project the queries, keys and values.
Okay, we don't start from transformer,
And the output is a vector, three type vectors.
Now, how do we use it? How do we use all these H1, H2, H3? We give a weighted sum, right, we put them together, very straightforward.
Okay, these three may be have some higher weight, and the others, tokenizer, okay, maybe, or evaluation, okay?
And the key and the values comes from the encoder.
You times the score, 2 times value, 2, and you sum them together.
but we instead we still need to reveal Rn, okay.
Okay.
You have a query where you want to learn something.
And then we save the same, the reports, really the reports.
So this loss every position in the decoder to attend all positions in the input,
Okay, his data, our complete new representation.
something called a residual connection, they simply plus the original input, several layers
OK, when you write to the formula, becomes this.
Okay.
Many times with different linear projections, but lower dimension, okay,
You already know something, okay?
That means, okay, X is here.
Maybe lower weight, they're all.
But we, we don't stop after we calculated this H2.
the sequence, the natural decoder, the decoder,
This key concepts are key related to a lot of things called values.
Rn plays the encoder, anti-coder model,
Hjj from 1 to Tx, alpha 1 to 4.
You don't need to learn X.
Okay, after you get this weight, what do you do?
Okay.
We weighted some all these hidden states into one wekt, okay, into one wekt as the input to decoder.
Now H2 prime is the combination of H, uh, of the input.
You start to recall the value, the real content, okay, for R&N, a lot of things, or feel forward neural network, a lot of things.
ago, or the original input into the network. Okay, the formula is y equals to fx plus x.
quite popular before transformer is published, okay.
Again, you need to learn something different.
attend to all the input sequence.
OK, alpha ij, alpha i means here.
comparing to let's say map all the input into 500 and 12 dimension,
But we don't think values first, okay?
So that's, I think, you might own understanding,
We use this query to query your memory.
Okay, so attention, then we see this, the embeddings, embeddings.
Okay.
Also encoder and decoder.
Uh, of course, uh, multiply with matrix and the previous hidden state.
that's explanation, okay?
Comparent to previous while only H3, but now we have H1, H2. So H3 is one of the special cases, right, is 0, 0, 1, the weight, 0, 0, 1, we got H3.
Yeah, there is the output.
So what is encoder?
And then, okay, you get the output, you get the output.
So which part, which key is most related, you get a score.
The motivation, very simple, okay?
You can, from the name, you can try, you can guess, okay.
OK, now we don't touch many queries.
query, key value, but in map, to 8, 6 dimension matrix, same calculation,
Okay, so the network actually lies, the new things, fine, tune the things, not the original information.
The model forget previous things we added.
Okay.
So the input embedding we use learned embeddings, okay,
So the final output is the value, but it's not one single value of a two value, but it's a weighted sum of all the values.
Okay.
The encoder is a component that takes input
That's it.
Many queries comes first.
Okay.
And after you, there should be some software max.
to convert the input tokens, output tokens to vectors,
Okay.
See?
But we can know sometimes because of that, they are not a same number of dimension.
Different layers.
When we write into the formula, this is the alpha.
and it comes worse, the input into a meaningful
And so this network will not forget the information, then you can have a very deep neural network,
Yeah, after you get a score, you go through a software max, okay?
Okay?
to dimension D model.
but they get more better results.
I forgot, okay, we add this.
internal representation.
But now we give H2, H1 sum of tunities, right, give you some weights that input into every hidden state.
So what's this?
Okay?
All the knowledge you have, okay?
Or sometimes we want to add some more information.
So in my understanding, what does this mean?
And do embedding, embedding, let's say.
You put a number into a formability distribution.
So this reminds me the area roots of Banyatri,
OK, the weight.
That's our human understanding.
that means many, many layers. Because the input is a sequence, we need the position information.
You get the idea, you want to, the query is something you are studying now, you want to learn something,
Actually, we don't know this, but we think,
These are the values.
So we, uh, times, uh, with matrix here.
What does this mean?
And then you give a weight to every value.
I mean, give you one single large matrix, comparing to give you 8 smaller matrix,
And we also use the URL and linear transformation, the software max function here.
you forget, you forget, okay?
okay, the semantic meanings are hidden
Here, the key has a transpose, but we don't have transpose.
Okay.
Give you a root of X.
Okay, but still have some problem for for each hidden state. All these context vectors remains the same.
Uh, so this hidden state is, uh, times multiplied by, uh, with matrix and plus, uh,
Okay, sometimes in the relative position information, so people in one, this positional
Go back, okay?
And then you sometimes the weight, some other output.
in this internal representation.
Directly.
you need to recall some knowledge, this knowledge, values, you cannot recall all the knowledge you have, but you can recall some sum of the knowledge.
So this is value 1.
A linear transformation software max function to convert the decoder output
Okay?
Residual connection.
Value 2, value 3, value 4.
So what are representations, just vectors, okay.
I hope you'll know this.
people find the result is better when you have multiple smaller matrix,
is not a single token anymore. Plus a positional embedding. So for position or index,
You have the weight.
to predicted next that token probability.
And again, normalization, okay?
You select some valuable part from your whole memory.
That's the vectors.
You have the weight.
the original hidden state.
Different concept already, new concept, normalization.
The internal values, the numbers in this middle layer, okay.
Okay, so what's that?
You calculate the matrix you get output.
Okay.
So apparently let's say the English sentences are IE2, IE4, have some words, have some verbs, nouns, some, not the nouns.
Uh, here we use a very special, uh, the unit matrix.
You attend to the input to some different positions.
How do you determine which knowledge, which sum knowledge you want to recall, you need to get, you need to compare, okay?
How to calculate the probability software max?
You know, in neural network, we don't want the value
so imagination, okay, the also suspect, suspect, right?
So we think the encoder, the function of encoder is,
So, uh, H2 prime becomes this value.
The one with highest probability is the ID, okay, is the ID, the token you want to predict.
So the first value, you get 0.1.
Okay, my pin are query and a set of key value pairs to an output.
there are 12345, it is not a number, it is a vector. The vector can help you find 112
inside the neural network becomes too large.
I also suspect, okay, we tell, basically we add more information.
okay, your input are sometimes.
Uh, clear.
So the first, the second value, you get 0.2, the third value, the first.
Compare the query and the key, compare the current knowledge you want to learn, and the concept you have, and then compare, compare means you get the weightage, okay?
We don't know the, you know,
So you, you can write, you can hear, we, you can see here, the input X mapped to a hidden state.
An output is computed as a weighted sum of the values.
We'll explain this later.
in the meaning space, semantic meaning space,
But when you translate, when you translate into French, sorry, I don't know how to translate French, but when you predict different French words, you may consider different parts of the sentence, right.
If you are calculating one big matrix, large matrix,
Normalization stops this.
Here is something interesting, okay, in our model we share the same weight matrix
So for the first dimension of the output, you calculate the weighted sum of the first dimension of all the values.
Normalization rescills values into a controllable range.
dimension. So how do you get the numbers of this dimension, they use two formulas,
so what are they, okay, encoder transfer this worse,
Where weight is computed by a compatibility function, okay?
We have, uh, with matrix here.
the model need to learn itself, okay, or the first dimension was kind of meaning, right?
between the two embedding layers.
But we add some arrow here.
So it prevents value from becoming too large or too small.
initial vectors into some meaningful internal representation.
Here is not a product of the query.
It is easy to understand the input, okay, and output.
This is the previous hidden state.
ones for the even dimension, ones for the odd dimension. Okay, that's all for today. So any questions,
It's a corresponding.
And, uh, with matrix WH and these two arrows point to the new hidden state.
This is a commonly used method, okay?
So the key idea is you don't need to reveal everything, but you need to select something important.
Then the sum is 3.
If you tell the model, okay, you learn 8 small matrix, basically you tell them,
And here, okay, sometimes you skew it, you divide it by the square root of D.
And how do we connect to next,
This is the first dimension, second dimension, third dimension.
So no matter French words, English words, use the same weight matrix.
This is a value, original value, minus the mean value,
If you translate I, I think you don't need to too much attention on the Apple or Apple. So can we give different context CI to each state I say.
OK, before we talk about two queries, I think we get one question.
how do we connect to decoder, decoder means output, right.
So we put into this R and N and you will get, okay, we are talking about this part, uh, this part.
okay, these 64 dimension learn different features from the other 64 dimensions, right?
Not important to us.
But how do you determine which part is important, you calculate the similarity, give some function, and you can't get a value, okay?
You're same vocabulary, okay, but here, the pre-softa max linear transformation,
if you don't have questions, feel free to leave them, see you tomorrow. Bye bye.
And for the decoder part, okay?
We think this final hidden state of the model
divided by the standard deviation.
Cool, this is a very good question.
Where does the key and the value come from?
Remember, you can now see the tokens.
It keeps the value centered and well-skilled.
represents the summary of the whole input sequence.
You have not predicted.
I will explain it later.
If you understand this part, then we go to, okay, what happened to the first one, right?
they also use the same matrix.
It comes from the same input.
And for the position, for each position,
Okay?
So in my understanding, okay, no proof, we give the model more instruction,
We think after we minus the mean, the new value,
That's the question. So when you predict every French word, can we consider different context. Although these context all comes from the same English sentence, but the weight is different.
The first one, just the previous hidden state is zero, uh, very simple.
This is interesting, okay, so here also use this one from ID to embedding.
There's a tension, any questions? Okay, a tension is the key part of this lecture, so maybe some, I will keep some time, but I hope you can understand, okay?
That's why we use previous hidden state
OK, let's say the first layer is the input.
it is not a number anymore.
the mean value of the new vector is there.
And if you write the formula, you will get this, you add the activation function, uh, this hidden state.
because we think, okay, this HY contents the information
It is a vector.
and this instruction help the model to learn things, okay, basically you tell them,
And the standard deviation is white, okay?
In the middle of the transformer, what is the input?
We don't want the values out of control.
They use the same matrix.
We call it normalization.
of input XY and H2, we constant HY,
It's output of last layer.
So we do some normalization.
It's one type, normalization.
okay, you 62 learn this feature one, you 62 learn feature two,
It's not only affected by the input, but also affected by the previous hidden state,
This is something new to me, I think, keep some information, keep the same,
Here, we do linear normalization.
This is a sample.
You can imagine, simply imagine these input are just vectors of the tokens.
We normalize into a values, smaller values around the arrow.
Suppose we have this vector, this vector,
because we include HY, the information HY, right.
The weight of each word is different. Okay, so we create all the word I say, but the weight is context.
A tension function is mapping a query, and a set of key value pairs to an output, where the query keys values outputs are all valid, okay?
but what are the feature one and the feature two, nobody knows, okay?
10, 12, 40.
So we believe H2, understand, okay,
semantic meaning information.
uh, both input and hidden state, previous hidden state have, uh, like, weight matrix, the parameter.
We calculate the mean 12 plus 12 plus 12.
And then you may have the positional encoding, here, plus something, something like sign,
So that's the idea, the idea is, okay, instead of you give one large matrix,
know something about XY, okay, and X2.
Okay, let's say, so if we still have any questions.
And then your times are parameter with matrix, then becomes q query, key and values.
And you calculate the standard deviation.
So this final state, okay, we believe,
Okay, clear.
If we still have time, let me show you this.
You normalize it.
Okay, we even, all people even create another set of weight for S2. If we have S3, we can add another set of weight C2 to S3 into formula, right into formula is this.
Okay, now then we go to today's lecture.
we calculate 8 smaller matrix, let's say, okay, so now we have 8,
sign, cosine, positional encoding.
this final state, HY, understand,
You can see, becomes values around the arrow.
So who is the query, who is the key, the query is the hidden state, the hidden state in the decoder, okay?
Today is, uh, important, I think, the call of the first half transformer.
or represent the whole context.
So why do we need the positional encoding?
This comes from the input, but not the same with the input.
Let's import this.
And the standard deviation is white, okay?
or 8, output, 8, output, what do we do?
Why so slow?
So what, how do we use this final HY,
Because it's self-attention, we don't know the order.
Okay, okay, this one, I think I talk enough.
It's mapped by some weight matrix.
Why we need this?
Uh, but today I'll introduce transformer, sorry, but we introduce the next study.
And the keys are hidden states in the encoder, you may notice this has two directions, so we ignore this, it doesn't matter, we don't teach this.
Okay, they simply concact the output, okay, concact the output,
Here is a sample.
It's the sigmoid function, the curve.
if I'm a little while, okay, we generate output already,
OK, what if we have many queries?
Because the output is weighted sub of the value, right?
Maybe I write.
So remember BP, BP name byte, play encoding byte.
The weighted sum of HG, but the parameters, the alpha, are different. If you write into the generalized formula, okay, for the ice context vector,
We only have one hidden state of the decoder.
Oh, mask.
Okay?
but now, not finished,
The value becomes very large, okay?
and then project into the, project into an output and for the following use, let's say,
You already put them all the values together, no matter when you learn or when you learn the knowledge put together.
Skill.Product attention.
because we want to generate the whole output sequence.
You do not predict one French token.
The scores.
Uh, sometimes now it's still processed byte, if we process the unit code characters.
Okay, the scores are calculated using q times k transpose.
The derivative value,
So we have a structure called decoder.
So the output is weighted sum of the values, so again who is the value, values also h, h, j in the hidden state of the encoder, so the output is context vector weighted sum.
You predict many French tokens.
OK, so this is a second query.
Skill by the dimension of the square root of the dimension of k.
it becomes there.
But here, we need some time, many times, we need the order of the sequence,
The decoder takes internal representation
Remember, uh, what, what is the input, what is the output?
The second query also, same thing.
okay, now you are, you imagine people, okay, we have 8 matrix calculate 8 times, no,
That means you know gradient,
You need to calculate the dot product between query second to key one, key two, key three, key four.
The input is the original words, right? The original, yeah.
and generates an output.
we use back propagation, and we need to calculate the gradient.
all every vector is weighted sum of hidden state HG, HG, HWF2 is RIN, okay. For each hidden state vector, we have value of it, okay, alpha G, alpha, alpha, alpha 2, alpha 3.
Go to softmax, you get the scores.
book, book, book, book, the sample, the bank, right?
Giving no, okay, decoder, the function is to generate
And the output is a set of large rules and some tokens, okay?
in the engineering part, when they write the code, they do not really calculate 8 times,
Oh, I think next lecture, I will explain,
the output tokens, the target tokens,
After you get the scores, you get weighted sum of values.
How do we decide the weightage, the weight assigned to each value is computed by a compatibility function, or the query with the corresponding key?
You get four scores again, the score second.
You need to know the position, context.
So we, we, uh, you can say we split, okay, some sample words into sample words.
a little about the atom, optimize,
but you need to have some material,
So each token embedding is augmented with a position dependent vector, position dependent.
The second score, one second score, two second score three.
they still use one large matrix, after they finish the calculation,
let the decoder to digest.
Okay, we return.
you know the back propagation,
And you're right into the matrix format.
Okay, what other material is the internal representation?
Different things.
you need to calculate the gradient.
And we, by handling these sample words, we may process.
Some parameter called mask.
When you update, in your network, you update the weight.
So what is a compatibility function, this is a compatibility function, you find some way calculate the relationship between these two vectors, between query and the key, it is okay?
This, the q is vector here.
That means, okay, for each position, position symbol, the index, right?
they simply split this into smaller matrix and put the values into the relative positions.
Mask positions are filled with a very large negative value.
But for context I, for the ice context, so we have another index here. So this value is alpha, IG. Okay, we don't need to go into this detail actually, but question comes. How to determine this, right, alpha, alpha G?
Yeah, this final HY, we think it knows
Uh, get, first get more information.
Query one, query two.
Uh, the second, you can handle some, uh, of what capability word, uh, in some words, you, you, you, you don't know, you can handle sample words.
And here is the transpose of key.
There are 12345, they put this position, transfer this position into a vector, vector, and plus,
all the whole context, the whole input,
The weights, you use weights equals to all weights,
When you have a very large negative value, softmax output is almost zero.
the way put this information,
So you will get q1, q2, key three, key four.
minus learning rate times graded.
and the initial HY, and state.
Uh, okay, input is one, so we, we, we, we, first of all, we split into characters.
So this is, just, I just mentioned this, okay, if you are interested, you can read the code,
And you can see this decoder also RRN, right.
If the graded is zero,
So why is an item called additive attention, but here it's called skilled dot product attention, okay?
That means k dot product between q1 dot product, between q1 and q1, between q1, q2, q1, q3, you get the first line.
added to the token embedding.
the weight does not change anymore.
Uh, two important, uh, data structure.
so people are really, really smart, really smart, so they don't need to create 8 different matrix,
So each token, now only how the token embedding itself, but also how the position, okay?
This prevents the model from attending to mask positions.
Decoder also RRN, but something different, okay,
So you cannot learn using the neural network.
You ask yourself, what do we have, how do we determine this value, what do we have? Actually we only have this hidden state, right.
One is what capability, uh, you know, which word, uh, everyone, each word, and uh, frequency.
You cannot learn using it.
the first, but in code, we know every input, right.
This function to not this attention.
So if the input is too large or too small,
We ignore skilled first, so it's dot product attention, that means, okay, we use dot product to calculate the relationship between query and key, okay?
And dot product between q2 and all keys, you get the second row.
they still using one large matrix and can do all the calculations, that's the beauty of programming,
the graded becomes close to zero,
So each position is represented by a vector, okay?
You create some random keys, values and queries.
But decoder, what is the input?
And then the second thing, you can't, uh, frequency, uh, five ground, player, statistic.
We don't know, we don't know the target centers,
it makes the learning very slow stop learning.
Not just a single number.
Now we want to determine this alpha values for hidden state S1, but we only have the value of S1 and all the hidden state.
And then you'll write the output.
we need to predict the target centers.
And then there's many people are confused, apart, okay?
This encoder, decoder, attention, that means we did that input mask.
And also, if the model is very deep,
but to me it is amazing, okay, so we continue the multi-head attention,
Okay, so people, you know what,
And then you'll merge the most frequently, up here, the way.
the values are repeated, they transform the multiply.
You calculate the output before the alpha is vector, but now it is a matrix.
this first token, okay, we will,
Sign, or very long formula, cosine, very long formula, but actually, quite simple, okay?
Clear?
this is not an important just let you know, so multi-head attention,
We did that even though the mask is not.
we will give you the first token,
How do you merge it?
Oh, too many other ones to repeat again, but it's not for query and assigned key value pairs to an output, output is computed as a weighted sum of the values, okay?
But here we generate some mask, Carol, Carol mask.
So they may explode when they make vanish.
the token began off sequence input,
Uh, okay, previous you held our vocabulary, right? Our vocabulary is L, uh, O, okay, white space, W, and the frequency is five.
allows the model to jointly attend to information from different respections,
So that's why normalization.
So very naturally we think we concerned the relationship, okay, concerned the relationship between this hidden state and each hidden state S, this S hidden state is hidden states from decoder, okay, the H is also hidden state, so the hidden state from encoder, okay.
Because we have two queries.
No, the mathematical principle, design and not simple, if we understand, we use it, it's quite simple.
you can generate the first HY, okay.
So we simply write in this way, query each row is a sample.
Something like this.
Okay, but what I said just normalize a vector
The first HY, not only rely on
It true for the cannot see.
respections, representation, subs with it, I also put in language, okay,
when you have batch data,
For the first item, you cannot see the future.
BGN, all sequence, nothing, right,
Key each row is a key, but here I have transpose.
And then you'll merge L, O, and W, to L, O, W, and update the vocabulary, okay?
this token has no meaning,
when you have a batch sequence data, what do do do?
but also affected by the internal representation.
For each token position, the transformer creates a vector, okay?
Okay, these values, so here is the weight, okay? The weight is computed by a compatibility function of the query with the corresponding key query corresponding key, okay?
different type of features, but nobody knows what are these features,
For the second item, you can see the previous one.
Go through software max.
When you process a batch of images, what do do?
Software max alpha matrix.
Now you have a new vocabulary, and then you can't, uh, frequency, so backgrounds, okay?
Okay, we believe this, then we get the very rich information
You cannot see the future.
We do it row by row.
So now you need to understand, for each position, each index, 01234, it's not a number, it is a vector.
This will not test this,
So that's not a fact.
so if you use a single attention, maybe the model cannot know,
Okay, so no mask.
from here, and then we generate the first output,
You can say with one only one vector.
And then you'll merge the most frequently, up here, the way.
You can see we call this function no mask.
but it's something you can read, very interesting.
So we want to calculate the, I want to determine a parameters of this alpha, IG, we only have hidden state from decoder ice and hidden states from encoder HY2, which is, so we have different methods, okay.
So basically you repeat them to one, three until some threshold is achieved, okay?
I don't know, okay, I need to learn different features,
Or have some values.
After map all the values into the values between zero and one, that means the probability.
that means the first French one,
Although a little bit something more skilled, dy by something, and you need to go through software.
And what is used?
and they learn everything, you want single matrix, so they say this diversity is lost due to average.
It has the same dimension with the token embedding.
The values are fake.
yeah, the first French one, and then,
I also don't need to take care of it.
This is a larger value.
oh, what's next?
So this BPE solve one thing, you solve the, uh, given, we, we are not simply given, uh, each word I ID, but we, we want it into sub words,
This is a small value.
How to apply this?
So they need to add them, add them together.
Then you may see a lot of this dash,
But if you apply the mask,
Some most of the time,
You calculate the weighted sum.
So we will use this sample, we use this sample to explain dot product attention, okay?
the line thing in Papers, okay,
this is zero.
you use the open source code.
Here you get different weights to different queries.
Okay, how do you transfer this 01234 into a 512, that dimension vector?
You know, people, the last people, they give some samples,
this means okay, the output,
If the mask is not now, it scores.
People already use this for you.
oh, decoder, as the input, oh, next step.
And you get the output.
from two different heads, from the encoder self-attention,
No matter the calculator, because it's matrix calculation,
Use layout now, write, transform,
we're too, too, too, too, okay? We get that, too, too, too, and what to work, solve another problem, okay?
So it is attention.
why do they use layout now?
Then a query, the model compares with all keys, right? You first you need to compute the weights using a compatibility function, right?
The, the, the, also, no more mathematics, that's it, right?
One of the methods we summed up, we just added them, so very straightforward, okay. Sometimes they have different dimensions, so we, times weight matrix, weight matrix to map to same dimension, and also of course add some information, we add them, okay.
That means okay, we support,
Why there is a scale?
all the values are there.
Why they don't use batch now?
although this token, the first French one is predicted,
and has learned different tasks, okay, some see the right line,
DK is dimension or key set values.
And they feel negative.
Okay, given each word, uh, embedding, okay?
So they start, start thinking, okay?
So you can only understand after you know all this.
This is some concept of normalization.
but we believe, okay, this is the input,
Okay, negative mask.
This embedding is not simple, uh, not random, given, it has some semantic meanings, uh, semantic meanings means,
How do they operate the instance samples?
it's more closed, okay, the local context,
For each i, the i means from 0 to 5,
A very large negative value.
and this is the data we have, right.
But not the strict people prove it using mathematics.
So this data, we need to be input
Always negative mask.
To compute the weights, different weights of different keys, query and different keys, okay?
a hundred and eleven, five hundred eleven, that dimension of the embedding vector.
Because here is easy for us to understand.
but the green lines a little bit, you can get a large context,
into this neural network, okay.
Just an experience.
if you use cosine similarity to the, the similarity, like, happy and glad, uh, they are, you will get quite high, uh, score.
Just let you know.
You can see here.
Then we go to remember this quantum wise fully connected
So you want additive attention, that's it, attention, okay, let me repeat, now we want to give the hidden state in decoder, every hidden state in decoder, give them different context, okay.
a little bit long distance, so the different head, learn different information,
So the second input is YY, YY,
You can see yourself and the previous one.
So large value of DK affects the performance of dot production.
So each dimension of the position, no embedding is defined as this.
Now we have a query, we have four keys here, so we want some method to generate four scores, okay? Because query need to, okay?
And then you apply the negative.
if you forward neural network.
so multi-head attention is just the same with self-attention,
The value may become very large with large values of DK.
and we generate hidden state as two, okay, as two.
Very long name, it is a few forward neural network.
This becomes true.
Okay, so this is a number, this is a number.
So how do we get this?
This becomes true.
Let's say a little bit different.
And again, the hidden state is not only affected
How do we get this embedding, okay?
Means this position is replaced by a negative e to the power of 9.
but it's another level, the level is we ask different attention head,
So how similar we are or how far, how distant, what's the distance, anything, okay? We have four numbers, so here we use dot product, dot product is not new to you, when we started the co-size similarity, we introduced this, okay?
So they suspect the authors.
The function is to calculate the different dimensions of the positional vector.
It applied to each position separately identically.
Given our set of words, of course, our set of sentences, the one I first, encoded by one hot, you get one hot vector,
by the input YY, okay.
Very experienced researchers.
we call it head, to learn different features, different meanings, that's it,
So that means okay, I want to translate this English,
That's a very large negative value.
That means when you translate, when you predict every French word, you want to focus on different parts of the English sentence, okay. Sometimes we focus on ice, sometimes we focus on eat, how do we give this different weight or a ton to different parts of the sentence, okay.
Let me just remember the input is sequence of data.
They suspect this large values will push the software max function into regions where the gradients are small.
Let's see.
Okay, after softer mask, almost there, almost there, and then all this.
okay, let me repeat that.
So position here is a number, it is fixed already, okay?
I want to translate this English sentence
that's the attention path, and then we go to encoder,
All the tokens in this sequence are input to the network.
into French, sentence.
and you get, uh, after your, uh, multiply away matrix, you map this one hot vector into a lower dimensional dense vector,
So, multi-hand attention.
After I know the first French one, okay, I guess,
They just use this formula to calculate the, the arrow dimension out of the 512 dimension for position 0, okay?
it means a little bit higher level attention is some formula,
Then I want to show you this positional encoding.
So they scale the dot products by the square root of DK.
I can start, guess, based on the English sentence,
And all the tokens times this fee forward neural network
So basically item wise, multiplication and sum number, okay?
this one in one box, now this encoder is part of the picture,
Because sometimes you'll see this image difficult to understand.
okay, now this S0 represents the whole English sentence.
same fee forward neural network identically and separately.
So basically, this value is too large.
and then you map again, okay? You, you use another way matrix map to a higher dimension, and then you predict the word ID, and you can calculate the loss.
each layer has two sub layers, so this copy from the paper,
And the first dimension, they use this formula.
And the first French one, we guess the second French one,
So we think if higher dot product values, this relevant speed to a query and key is stronger, okay?
I've read this.
We may affect the learning procedure.
Let's say, so that means the linear transformations
Run means because after you calculate the numbers,
okay, first is the multi-head self attention mechanism,
And the second dimension, they use this formula, okay?
We need to give different weightage to different hidden states HY2, which is three. The question is how do we determine the value of this weightage, okay.
So they divide it by something.
after we have the second French one,
are the same across different positions.
By something.
you have a long decimal number.
we have the whole English sentence,
Of course, this parameter is not a hard code number, but it is related to the data.
so after this course, I hope when you hear this multi-head self attention,
And that's the dimension, they use this formula, okay?
Okay, once you have the loss, you can update the parameter, and you, after you train the model, okay?
So for position wise,
So, around to four.
the first two French words, then we guess the third one,
And now, so this concept is easier, and now we want to answer the question, okay, what does this two matrix mean?
Later we show if we have time, we show this is difficult to, easy to confuse, actually not difficult to understand.
So, the position is a total of 16.
fully connected, fully connected,
you are very confident, you know, you can see I know every detail of this attention,
okay, it's a red circle.
it's not sparse and do not have the job hard thing.
So that's the input, that's the input.
So it may increase or help the learning procedure.
We take this vector as the word vector of every word, okay?
But the dimension of each position is a vector.
And then we have, we calculate the second hidden state,
Of course, layout to layout different parameters.
When we only have hidden state and these values, so some vector operation comes in the first simple wise, which simply sum, sum them, sum them, and go to what activity function transfer into a value, okay.
then the second is the position wise fully connected to FIFO neural network,
Because some people, many people, I mean also, you see this or what they, this, right?
The dimension of the vector is eight.
We have a family short break.
Because it's easy to understand, you calculate a vector to vector, you get a number, but when they write into matrix, it looks like a lot, difficult, actually, okay?
okay, similar as the second hidden state,
We have two, uh, model structures, this picture shows skip graph, okay?
You see, you first create a more space.
So what is this?
it's not only affected by YY and the input,
So attention is important.
So actually it's quite simple.
Daryl or X have linear projection times sparse.
okay, this is very very long confusing name,
Sorry, I talk a little bit more.
Oh my god.
but also affected by the previous hidden state.
And then apply the complex formula.
it's just a feed forward neural network, FIFO neural network,
So position meets the first English one, second English one, third, for each position, it is a vector.
That means from target word to context word, uh, continuous bag of words, the input context words, and the output target word,
We come back at 9.58.
What's it?
But people think, ah, if this sequence is too long,
Ralloo, Ralloo.
But I can see.
I will explain it later, a residual connection,
And I hope you understand.
For those values less than their row becomes their row.
So now you can see we have one query, right? Query is a vector, vector has three items, there's three numbers, okay? One, two, three, I just numbers, okay?
Any questions you can ask.
You remember the Python 192.
This additive attention, but transformer is different, so I talked to so many things, I'll introduce attention, now basically you have the idea what this, what does attention do, okay.
after you learn the computer vision module,
For those values greater than their row, it is itself.
we may forget, important.
I think it takes some time.
It is a vector, you need to calculate every dimension of the vector, right?
From there to the under step size is two.
You know, all the information comes from
I hope you know what is residual connection, okay,
comes from the English sentence, the input.
It's an activation function.
Are you supposed to submit something proposal?
From one to the under step size is two.
it is the previous one.
that's because this comes from computer vision,
Now we go to decoder.
How do you know the value?
That means all the information comes from S0,
We put it here, and for each key, we also have three numbers, but we have four keys, so the numbers must be be written in this way, okay?
But today we talk about transformer. transformer, uh, looks, uh, a lot of things, okay?
and also I will explain later, followed by a layer normalization,
When they design this formula for the even dimension, all the odd dimensions, they use different formulas, they use two formulas to calculate the value, okay?
So in the decoder,
So, for the different dimension,
give you, we vary S3 or Fuget.
we have access to all the tokens of input sequence,
I didn't check.
So now we give another simple example, okay, easy to understand. So first we give us some definition, okay. Attention function can be described as, my opinion are query and a set of key value pairs to an output.
different dimension, even dimension,
I created a job box for every group.
a layer normalization is quite useful concept,
and all the dimension get different values.
S3 Fuget, S0 already.
same routine.
You can put the file there.
And, uh, and also a lot of, yeah, not a concept, knowledge, but, but the most important thing is, attention.
Let me just go to the decoder.
Again, this is for each position.
but actually this is a series of normalization methods,
So people add one thing, you'll check this formula,
Y, Y, K, one, two, K, Y, three, okay? It's the first key, and for the last key, that's three numbers, okay?
This transformer is really classic.
Remember what's the function of the decoder?
It is a vector.
Even dimension, use y formula, all the dimension.
I hope you understand the principle.
Attention is all you need, uh, it really is true.
Predict the output one by one.
the hidden state, people add Y called context,
And if you draw a picture, the higher value, the more lighter.
Not only apply it.
sometimes I hope sometimes you take some time to learn,
There's a term autoregressive.
That's all from me.
Uh, but this, uh, if you are interested, you can.
Four, key, four, two, key, four, three, and if you want to calculate them,
If you understand this, maybe in the future you can read some.
Any questions?
context, we're,
You predict the token one by one.
Thank you for...
But...